Hi, welcome back to Arya Nagarguna. This
this is the review class.
And we've had 14 amazing classes. We
have gone through
uh I think it's nine chapters,
which is a big achievement. That's a
third.
It's not a third of the amount of text,
but it's a third of the chapters cuz the
chapters have different lengths, and
these are shorter chapters.
But definitely we've done a huge piece.
It's it's about 20% of the whole wisdom
text of Nagarjuna and the commentary by
Tony Lama, which is to say the
commentary by Tsongkhapa also.
And we made great progress. We worked
through it very hard. And I thought, you
know,
let's have some fun. Let's just relax. I
have seven of my friends here.
And let's just
uh
let's just talk about what we just
studied, okay?
And maybe it'll be fun for you guys at
home also uh to
to to listen to us wander around in the
dark, as they say.
Uh
so here we go.
Uh we started with chapter nine.
And uh that's called an investigation
about who might have been there before.
It's a weird name for a chapter, right?
It's an investigation
about who might have been
there before we got there or something
like that. Who might have been there
before. I'm going to show pictures, and
my esteemed friends
are going to guess
what we were talking about
with that picture, okay? And of course,
I will give you clues cuz I was careful
to study it before I came
cuz I also don't remember, okay? So here
we go.
First picture, Dr. Butchy.
Anybody want to explain briefly what's
going on and I'll repeat it for the
recording. Okay.
I'm just briefly, what's going on?
There's a young girl.
She has a telescope.
She goes outside.
To look at the stars, but
before she looks at the stars, is she an
astronomer
astronomer or not? Good, good, good.
Okay, so which came first, the
astronomer or the stars?
It's a joke, right?
Yeah, she came out first, guess what?
No, but she wasn't an astronomer yet.
Why?
She wasn't looking at the stars yet.
Wait, so she has to look at stars before
she's an astronomer. Yeah, you cannot
call her an astronomer
until she looks at the stars. So, the
stars came first, right?
And then and then later she became an
astronomer. So, she didn't come out of
the house first, right?
You see, this is the problem, okay?
Because of the wrong way that we look at
reality,
uh we are always confused about how
things work, okay? Always. Even with
just somebody
looking at something, we don't
understand.
And and this chapter
uh
was specifically about the sense
powers. And how do you look at
something? How do you hear something?
How do you smell something? How do you
taste something? How do you feel
something?
Which comes first, the object or the or
the scene?
When you look at a wall,
was the wall there before you looked? Or
did you open your eyes and then the
seeds in your mind open and then the
wall was there
to see?
Right? So, maybe it's backwards of what
we think, you know? It's not that you
open your eyes and see a wall.
It's that you open your eyes and make a
wall
to see, okay? And it doesn't feel like
that. It feels like the wall was there
before.
Okay, so
that can apply to the medicine of the
mantra, for example.
So, you say the mantra and then you
think the mantra
changes somebody's cancer or something
like that.
So, so the the mantra comes first,
right?
And then the can- then cure the cancer,
right? No.
Why?
Because until you cure cancer with some
magic words, they are not magic words.
They're not mantras. Mantra means words
of power.
Until they show their power, they are
not mantras.
Okay, so can you say the mantra before
the cancer is cured?
Can you say a mantra before the cancer
is cured? Yes or no?
No, you cannot.
It's not a mantra until they get cured.
So,
you have to think about it, okay?
If the guardian of says, "If you don't
understand this point, I don't care if
you say mantras. You know, maybe you get
lucky and they cure somebody
because they did something good 10,000
lifetimes ago.
But if you want the mantra to cause the
cure, you have to understand that the
mantra is not a mantra until the cure
comes, which means the mantra is
impossible to to cause the cure.
So, something else is happening here.
It's not the mantra
causes the cure.
It's that your mind creates a mantra,
your mind creates a a meditation
session, and then your mind creates a
cancer cure. Duh
duh duh not duh duh duh. Okay? So, don't
do mantras thinking that the mantra is
going to kill a person.
Save life. Protect life.
Help other people's life. I saw a funny
thing today. I took a picture of do for
you.
Uh there's a new word in the corporate
world.
It's called greenwashing.
Like whitewashing. So, in in in English,
American English,
whitewashing means you did something bad
and then you whitewash it and it looks
good, you know.
And now there's a new word for in
corporate world called greenwashing.
And it means you take credit for carbon
sequest
during that you didn't really do.
You see what I mean? You say, "Oh, look,
I saved 50 trees." And somebody says,
"Where's the trees?" And you're like,
"Well,
And it's called greenwashing now. It's a
new verb in in American industry. Why am
I talking about that?
It looks like the mantras is causing the
cancer to go away, but really
saving lives of animals, for example, by
by saving the environment and
sequestering carbon, okay? Which is a
huge saving animals. You can save a few
fish.
But what if you save the whole world's
animals?
That would be cool.
Then your mantras will work
to to create to to stop cancer. Okay,
got it?
Because the mantra comes from you.
Saying the mantra comes from you.
And the cure comes from you. And it's
not that saying the mantra causes the
cure. Got it?
You have to save life before you do the
mantra or the mantra won't work, okay?
That's the intention of the mantra.
Cool.
All right. That's, by the way, how you
can get a cure before the mantra exists.
Okay?
All right, let's go to our next picture.
By the way, that was
I'm happy that you guys knew what
picture it was.
Uh, this is a tough one. You guys ready?
Uh uh-oh, I'm on the wrong one.
And let's see here.
No, I think it's the next one.
It's a fire maybe.
Yeah, okay, good.
It's the next picture, right? Okay, now
we're on chapter 10, which was called
If you look at the picture, you can
guess.
An investigation of
fire and firewood. All right, so now
we're on the next chapter.
And I want to know how chapter 10 is
connected to chapter 9, $100.
Chapter 10 is about fire and firewood.
Chapter 9 is about
how does the eye work?
And chapter 10 was about the
the pictures.
Yeah.
Yeah. How does fire burn the wood?
Which is similar to
Was there an astronomer before human
eyes?
Yeah. Okay, roughly. I'll give you 75.
Okay, yeah. Here we go.
Uh
chapter 9 was about how do you see an
object? How does the subject interact
with the object, okay?
Chapter 10, if you remember
who brought up the fire and the
firewood?
Yeah.
The other guy. The other guy. He said,
"Look, the guy didn't quit overworking
your mind.
Okay? Look, it's simple. It's the same
way that fire and fire burns wood.
The way that the eye sees the wall
is the same as the fire burns the wood.
Why you making so complicated? You know?
And then the guy just says, "Oh, you
don't think it's complicated when you
burn or burn wood with the fire? Let me
ask you some questions."
Okay, so that's why I have this picture
of people sitting and doing what to the
fire?
Looking at the fire. I was trying to
bridge you from chapter 9 to chapter 10.
Okay? Chapter 9 is about how do you see
the wall?
Chapter 10 is what's really happening.
When fire burns what?
What kind of wood?
But before the fire burns the firewood,
how can you
firewood
call it firewood?
Okay?
Okay, let's go to the next one.
What is the next one?
Now, we definitely have a problem here.
You're not guys aren't showing them in
the same order or something.
Yeah, they should be in the same order.
I think the next one is still in the
bring No, forget numbers. Stick to the
order that finder puts them in.
No, okay. Well, I think the next one is
lighting a cigarette. I think we're
still in
I'm sorry. I I saw a finger. Okay. Oh,
there we go.
All right, now.
Now, I'll give you a clue and you tell
me what's going on here.
The the
the flame is not touching the cigarette.
That's a clue.
What Why did I choose this picture?
I'll I'll start I'll start the
conversation, okay?
Is the fire
the firewood
or not?
No.
No, that fire acts on the firewood,
right?
Yes.
So,
uh let's just confirm. This is how you
do it the big way.
Let's just confirm.
No problem. You always say no problem.
Is the fire the fire one?
No.
No. So, the fire's acting on the fire
one, right?
Yeah.
Yeah. So, they're separate things.
You go like this in the debate.
So, they're separate things, right?
Yes or no?
Yes.
Do they ever touch?
No.
No. Okay. So, you can light a cigarette
by uh opening a lighter 10,000 mi away
cuz they don't have to touch.
Right? So, I was trying to find a
picture
that had a little bit of space between
the
the flame. I mean, it that space could
be 10 million miles. It doesn't matter,
okay?
If the fire
is not the cigarette,
then where do they touch? Where can they
touch, okay? Where's the point of
contact between the cigarette and the
and the fire?
Okay? If they never touch,
then you can't light a cigarette with
the fire, okay? If they do touch,
then there's a part of the
cause
which touches the result. Am I right?
And in that case, something in the past,
which is already gone, can affect
something in the present.
Yes.
No. It's gone. It It If it's gone for a
millisecond or it's gone for a million
years, it doesn't matter. It's gone. It
can't
burn your finger.
Something in the past can't burn your
finger and it cannot light a cigarette.
Or else do they exist at the same time?
Okay.
Anyway, what's the point, Geshe La?
Why are we talking about all this stuff?
Let me do my massive Buddha mantras.
Don't hassle me.
I'm trying to say, by the time you
finish the mantra,
it's gone and it cannot cure cancer.
Something from a million years ago
cannot cure cancer. And something from
one half of a second ago cannot cure
cancer cuz it's gone and it doesn't
exist. And it can't touch anything if
it's not here. Okay?
Mantras cannot cure cancer.
It can't be like that. Well, guess what?
I heard many stories people cured their
cancer by saying mantra. No.
Your mind created the person saying
talking a mantra. Your mind created the
sound. Then your mind created the cancer
being caused. If you want to cure
cancer,
good, say mantras, but first collect the
karma.
What's the karma? Sequester karma.
Okay, save a billion animals. Save a
million How many there's 80 billion
animals I think. I looked it up some
uh in the world. Okay? So, if you fix
the
over what do you call it?
Overheating problem of the atmosphere.
And then it's climate
Climate change.
Then you're going to save 80 what? 50
billion animals. Let's do that. Then
then then you can say mantras and
everything will happen. All kinds of
good stuff will happen. Guess what?
We'll get croissants every 5 minutes.
Okay.
Impossible things.
All right, next picture.
Is it the
Yeah. What is this? And be prepared to
prove it.
What's the What's in the picture?
It's a pile of firewood.
Yeah, why is it firewood?
Firewood is not
firewood until it is
Until you start a fire. Until it burns.
Therefore, this cannot be firewood cuz
it hasn't burned yet. Right?
Same thing, okay? Don't get confused.
Uh by the way, we're still in what
chapter? Uh, chapter 10. We're still
investigating firewood.
Uh, the guardian who spends a lot of
time on chapter 10. It seems to be
important to him. Okay.
All right, let's look at our next
picture.
Yeah, uh, we're still in chapter 10.
And
we're talking about dependent
origination.
What's the short way to describe
dependent origination? What was the
first thing Lord Buddha said
when he taught dependent origination?
Yeah, if this happens, then that
happens. He didn't say there's 12 wings,
there's a long way out. He didn't say
that. He said, "What?
If this happens, that happens." He's
probably going like this.
If this happens, that happens. Get it?
Okay. It's not dependent origination.
Okay, later they put a big name on it.
But the very first time he explained it
was like, "If this happens,
then that's going to happen." It's just
like what your mom used to say,
you know? If you do this,
you're going to have that happen.
Your mom tried to teach you, right?
So, that's uh, cause and effect. So,
what that means is
think about it. The second thing to
happen
depends on the first thing to happen.
Got it?
If you do this, this is going to happen.
Now, if you talk about dependence,
the second thing to happen is depending
on the first thing to happen, right?
It's like, uh,
here's the coffee cup or here's the
handkerchief.
So, this is the
this is the thing that happened and this
is the cause. The cause supports the
result, right? If you do this, honey,
you're going to get that, honey.
Okay? Because that depends on this,
doing this. Getting that depends on
doing this, right? So, there's a
dependent relationship.
Results rest on causes, right?
No.
By the time you the result comes out,
the cause is long gone.
Okay? There's no such thing as
dependence. You can cancel all of
Sugeng's translations.
Okay? It's all impossible.
Why?
Cuz to have dependence,
the thing that happens second have to
depend on the thing that happens first.
And if the thing that happens first is
already gone, then
there's no dependence. Just the
handkerchief falls on the floor.
Got it?
All right. So, that's what it really
means. So, where's the dependence?
Now, $100 question. Let's go to that
last picture.
The parts of the pen.
I say something is depending on
something in this picture.
I say
something is depending on something in
this picture. For $100.
Somebody tell me who has depending on
what's on on what.
I thought you'd say that.
Anybody else want to try?
The ink depends on the seeds.
Yeah, good. $100 for Pujan. Okay?
Yeah, the pen depends on the seeds. This
is a trick picture.
This picture is a trick. Guess what I
was going to say. Oh, what's depending
on what? And Gelson's going to say, "Oh,
the pen's depending on the table." And
then Pujan's going to say, "No, the pen
is depending
on my seat. Got it? Okay, that's all.
That was a clever picture, I guess.
I don't know. After I die, who's going
to
remember what this picture is?
All right.
Here we go, next one.
Wait. Man,
isn't there Maybe I'm in the wrong
place.
Uh,
let me check this.
Uh
B B B
B
Okay.
Wow, this is really weird.
Okay, we got the bundle of firewood.
We got the pan on the desk.
Oh, right, you're right. Okay, good. Uh
The other guy said, "Look,
uh you can see
that the
fire comes from the firewood. For
example,
look, the guy is going to I don't care
you say the fire is the firewood
or you say the fire is separate from the
firewood,
it doesn't really matter. If you put a
match on some dry wood, it's going to
burn. You know, I don't care what kind
of philosophy you have.
You know, I can burn your house down.
Watch me.
Okay, then you can philosophize all
sides about it.
But anyone can see
that when you put a match near a bunch
of dry stuff,
it burns. Okay? And then the guy is
going to replies with this picture.
What's the point of the picture?
Take off your glasses, your eyes will
still see it.
Well, I'm saying
why did I use colored glasses here?
And just because you see it that
way.
Yeah, just because you see it that way
it doesn't mean
that it's correct.
that it's correct. Yeah, your eyes are
your equipment is broken. That would be
the guy is going to answer. Okay? In
fact,
listen to this. Everything in the wheel
of life is broken, okay? Got it?
And it took me many years to figure that
out. If something is painted
in the wheel of life,
inside the wheel, inside the edges of
the wheel, it's broken.
Okay, everything there is effed up.
Everything, okay? So,
your eyes, which are Naba Kichu,
fifth link,
okay? The buildings, the empty
buildings,
they are broken. They are broken. Your
eyes are broken.
Don't tell me
fire burns wood
because I can see it.
If you Okay, is everything pink in the
world? You know, I don't know.
Is my white phone pink?
Why? Why do you say that, Geshe La? Cuz
if you have pink eyeglasses on, it's
going to look pink to you.
Okay? And you always have these
eyeglasses on. You were born with these
sunglasses on, and you will wear them
until the day you die. You are born
with a defect in your eye. What's the
famous example about a defect in your
eye?
Cataract, cataract.
Yeah, which kind of means you have a
scratch on your eye on your cornea,
and you think there's some
Hair on the seat.
Or you think there's a crack in the
porcelain. You think and it's really
just
a scratch on your eyeball, okay? So,
according to Buddhism,
of course your mind is misunderstanding
everything, but the problem is worse
than that. Your eyeball is broken.
You always see things the wrong way,
okay? When you think you see a a match
causing a fire, or when you think a
mantra is curing cancer,
you are
there's a problem with your eyes, okay?
It's not That's not what's happening.
What's really happening, Gisela?
You saved a bunch of animals' lives by,
I don't know, planting a forest in Bear
Mountain.
And then that oxygen saved many animals
and and
then you did mantras and you can cure
cancer. Got it? Okay? That's all.
If the guardian is correct, we have to
be nice to animals and other humans as
well.
All right, next one.
This picture is connected to this. For
$100, tell me why.
This picture is connected to this.
Fire, cook, pizza.
Yeah, good. $100 for the young man.
Did Oh, you just you're self-reporting,
okay? If you don't report, it's not my
problem.
Uh
At what point is the pizza done?
At what point is the pizza done? Okay?
At what point So, there's past fire,
there's future fire,
and there's the fire in the moment,
right? And that keeps moving.
The present moment keeps moving. What is
the perfect point? What cooked the pizza
perfectly, by the way?
You made dinner for somebody else 2
weeks ago, and you didn't burn it.
Okay?
Okay? You made dinner for somebody 2
weeks ago, you didn't burn it. Then you
went to Rotten Johnny's and bought a
pizza, and it was perfect.
Why? He found the impossible line
between undercooked and overcooked,
okay? Where's the line between
undercooked and overcooked?
Yeah, where does the part of the room
you walked on already meet the part of
the room you didn't walk on already? Cuz
they're both gone.
One happened already, one hasn't
happened yet. They're not there. Where
do they meet? They can't meet anywhere,
they're not here in the room.
It's all coming from you. When you walk
through a door, what's really happening?
Yeah. Small picture, bigger picture,
take it up the door frame.
Small picture, bigger picture, bigger
picture, bigger picture, small picture,
small picture. I read a nice book once.
It was a little win.
Uh it's a short story. It's about a tree
that got overworked.
Why?
It's a very old tree. It's like
500-year-old tree.
In the old days, when people walked or
had wagons,
life was bearable.
What do you mean?
Well, as they got closer to me, I had to
grow.
And then as they walked away, I had to
shrink. And I you know, it was okay, but
now 80 miles an hour, I mean, how the
goddamn expect me to grow and shrink
uh
in a 10th of a second? It's too
stressful. The tree was complaining
about I have to grow as they get closer
and then I have to shrink really fast as
they drive away. It's too much. It's too
bad, you know.
Okay, that's what's really happening.
Thank you, tree.
All right, here we go.
Yeah, and and and what's the favorite uh
What do you call it?
He's not bitching, it's uh
similar.
Gishla is always cavetching.
Yeah, cavetch is good. Gishla is always
cavetch. Gishla is always making some
statement regarding a turtle. For $100,
who can tell me?
What's the statement Gishla likes to
make about this particular turtle?
If you think that the world is
your is carried on
On the back?
of the turtle
Yeah.
Then that means that everything is in
the world you think how it is made is
wrong.
Good. Yeah, $100 for Don't forget to
tell my boss.
Okay, yeah.
So, I don't know, 3,000 years ago in
India
people believed the whole world was
being held up by a turtle.
You know, and that it was flat and it
was being held up by a turtle, okay?
If you misunderstand
how the whole world
happened
then you misunderstand everything in
your life, okay?
If you If you misunderstand
how fire burns wood
then you you you must misunderstand
mantras, for example. You must. You have
to.
Okay? And And I'll give you a
possibility.
How many people in ancient India
understood the shape of the world?
Correctly?
Zero. Zero. Call it 10 million, 50
million. God knows how many were alive
at that time.
How many percent of them were wrong?
100% Okay, 100%.
So, it's In theory
it's possible that we are also wrong
100%. In It has happened
in the past
that people had the wrong idea
about how much stuff
everything.
You got to say it like that.
Everything, okay?
And maybe we're also wrong about
everything, okay?
All right. So, then if you're wrong
about fires
or you're wrong about how plants grow
or you're wrong about how your husband
yells at you?
Then maybe you're wrong about
everything. Wives are wrong more than
husbands. Can I say that to you? I think
it's true.
Okay.
Just kidding.
Okay. It's always the husband in the
kitchen, right?
Okay. Anyway,
just consider the possibility.
If Nagarjuna is correct in this book if
this book is correct,
then everything you think is wrong.
And that means
every action you ever took in your life
is wrong.
The when you turn the switch to turn on
this light,
it was a mistake.
That was based on a misunderstanding.
When you turn the key to start your car,
you're you're insane.
Okay.
You should be looking for someone to
give a ride.
Okay. Then try to start your car. Okay.
Um
Otherwise, your car might
not start someday, which of course never
happens.
Okay, next one.
This this picture by the way, we're on
to chapter 11.
So, this is the third chapter we worked
on. By the way, not every class was a
separate chapter. Some classes took
some chapters took more than one class.
Uh but we did chapter 11. Chapter 11 is
called an investigation of a first
beginning and a final ending to things.
Is there a first beginning and is there
a final ending to things? When they
asked the Lord Buddha,
you know, did the universe have a did
samsara have a beginning? Does samsara
have an end? What did he say?
What did he say?
Well, yeah, but then
what was the question? They didn't say,
is there? They said,
Yeah. is it is it evident to you?
Remember,
is it evident to you? Good, okay.
And so this picture is meant to
to describe
Okay, if you ask me does everything have
a beginning, I can answer you on two
levels.
If you ask me does everything have a
beginning,
I can answer you on two levels. On an
obvious level,
I can say no because everything has a
cause, therefore nothing has there is no
beginning to everything, okay? On a
deeper level,
why do we think anything begins?
When did this class begin?
About a hundred years ago.
When your when
when the seeds in your brain mind open,
okay?
This class on a deeper level,
this class had no beginning.
The class didn't start,
your seeds opened. Got it?
Don't ask me did the class start. Don't
ask me how long ago the class started.
Did you notice I'm not using timer
anymore?
I don't care.
Don't ask me when the class started. I
don't care. The class started when your
seeds opened. You can answer your own
question. Don't ask me how many minutes
went by, and that's not the answer.
That's why Buddha, when they asked him
this question originally, he said
What was his first answer to this
question?
Lunga then.
Well, that means he refused to answer,
okay? He refused Don't ask stupid
questions. Hey Geshe-la, what time did
the class start? How many minutes ago
did the class start? Don't ask me stupid
question.
Why is it stupid question? It started
when your seeds opened, got Don't blame
me.
You created the class.
Okay, it's your problem if it goes on
too long.
That's your fault.
Go to the bathroom, man.
Yell at the mirror.
That's the DCI.
Probably have to pay a a commission to
the DCI now.
Okay, I'm just kidding.
Okay, what's next?
Uh this was described uh as uh the
difference between making something out
of nothing and making something out of
something. Everything is artificial.
The world is artificial, okay? There is
nothing real.
How How much of the world is artificial?
Everything. Okay?
So, is it empty? Yes. Does it exist?
Yes.
Is it real? Well, yeah. I mean, go Go
out and stand in front of a car and tell
me what happens.
It's still breaking.
But it's But in the one sense, it's not
real. It's coming for me.
Okay, and by the way, we are still in
chapter 11
trying to see if anything ever started
or anything ever stopped.
So,
is it artificial?
Yes. Did it happen?
No. Did it happen from you? Yes.
Got it?
Okay.
All right, let's go to the next one.
We are now moving to chapter 12, which I
will remember
which as I will remind you
was an investigation
of whether pain was created by
pain or something else.
And then the the title of the chapter
can be read differently.
Was the pain in your life created by you
or by someone else. Is the trouble
in your life your fault or your
husband's fault or your wife's fault,
okay? Is the trouble in your life
created by you or by somebody else? Or
you can say does pain cause pain or does
non-pain cause pain? That's There's two
ways to read the chapter title.
And we have four possibilities.
Uh number one. And by the way, these are
representing four different schools of
ancient thought. And that's how we
started this chapter. Where does pain
come from? Number one.
Was pain caused by itself?
Which is the Sankhya position. Did God
create pain?
Okay? Second position.
Uh is the pain caused by something other
than Michael? Okay? When Michael touches
the cactus and gets pain, did something
outside of Michael hurt Michael? And we
say, yeah, I mean, you could say that.
Was it both? Okay? Both God and
something else.
Jane said that, okay? There's a religion
in India that says that.
And then uh did it just happen and
nobody made it happen?
That's a position by the Charvakas.
Which is a certain school of ancient
India, okay? Who don't believe in karma.
All right. So, these are four
possibilities, okay?
We normally say pain is caused by
something other than me, right? Like the
cactus caused
The cactus hurt my finger.
Okay. Let's go to the next one.
Now,
this is almost the only normal argument
I allowed in this class, in this whole
course.
This one's normal argument.
If I say to you,
the pain of this employee
is being caused by someone else or by
him, What's your answer?
The employee is in pain, okay? If you
If you've ever been an employee in a big
company, you go through this like every
day.
Okay? Who caused the trouble for the
employee?
Who's hurting the employee?
Himself, okay? That's all. I mean, I
tried to put one normal thing in the
picture, okay?
It looks like
the boss is
hurting the employee.
There's two famous problems in life. One
is how your boss treats you, and one is
how your spouse treats you.
There's just two.
I mean, kids are probably a subset of
spouses.
Uh
And this is so common. If you've worked
in a big company, you know, somebody's
yelling at you, somebody's hurting you.
Who's hurting? Is he being hurt by
himself, or is he being hurt by someone
else?
By himself, okay? He's being hurt by
himself.
Okay, that's an easy
That was a normal question.
All right. We're on to chapter 13.
And chapter 13 was called an
investigation of factors. And what
should have You with the question you
should have asked yourself was why did
they teach this chapter in addition to
which chapter?
Come on. The first chapter.
The first chapter is called an
investigation of
conditions.
Causes and conditions.
And now, 13 chapters later, they're
using the same thing? Factors?
What's that all about? It should have
been named This chapter should have been
named an investigation of
This This is a clue in the picture.
Real and unreal. Yeah. Fake and
fake and real.
Or an investigation of illusion.
That would be a better name for this
chapter. Okay? It's really an
investigation of illusion.
Now
Got to ask you
Okay, let's let's take that one. Use
that one. Use the purse.
Use the purse. Okay? Now
Is it real or not?
It's real but
Yeah, it's real but it's fake. Good.
It's real but it's fake. No, it's fake
but it's real. I'm sorry.
Okay.
It's fake but it's real. What do I mean?
It's a fake
It's a It's a imitation.
Yeah, it's a fake Gucci but
It actually
You can still carry your wallet around
in it. Okay? Got it? Fake real.
No, sorry. A real fake.
Okay? Is it what it looks like? No.
Can it work? Yes. Is the world what it
looks like?
No. Does it work? Yes. If you don't
believe me, go stand in front of a car
and tell me what happens.
Does the illusory
steel in the bumper break your illusory
leg? Yes.
Okay. We're not saying nothing matters
or nothing's real.
Okay.
The guy Now the other guy says, "Look.
Uh
do the leaves change in the autumn?
Okay? Do the Does the color of the
leaves change when the autumn comes?
Does Do the leaves change from green
to yellow?
Yes or no?
Yes.
Yeah.
So
were they green to start?
Yeah.
So did they have an identity when we
start. Were they green?
Were our green leaves green?
Yes, so they have a nature. They're
green. If they didn't have a nature of
green, how could they change to another
color?
If green was not in them,
how could they become yellow?
Okay, got it? That's a good That's a
fair question.
If they weren't green in themselves,
why do you say they turned yellow?
Okay?
All right. Now, here's the next
argument.
Uh oh, by the way, we say uh if they
were green, they never would have
changed to yellow.
Okay, that's all.
Your argument proves that you're wrong.
Okay, all right. Uh
$100 for this one.
It's a tough one.
I'll give you a clue. It has to do with
emptiness.
And uh
Come on, think about it.
Did I tell you a joke about the abbot of
the monastery?
Did I tell you about that story?
No, no, it's a different thing. I guess
I forgot to tell you the story.
What's Gaye?
Gaye is the end of the summer retreat.
So, for 3 months in the summer, all
ordained people are supposed to stay
inside mostly. Why?
So, you don't step on bugs. So, in
India, in the summer monsoon, after the
monsoon,
there's millions of bugs around. If you
step anywhere, you will kill lots of
animals. Therefore,
you know, in general, try to stay at
home.
It's like virus and what do you call
lockdown? You know, in general trying to
stay at home and stay firm.
Don't go out. If you can help it, don't
go out. That's summer retreat. Guyi
means
then you're allowed to come out and it's
just like nowadays in Arizona, everyone
came out. Okay? Everyone came out. That
you can't get a restaurant reservation
at all for this week. Forget it.
Uh
that's why we have to play our own rock
and roll.
So, uh
you know,
people come out and in the monastery, uh
you can play games for 1 week.
And you can play a radio. You can play
board games. You can play soccer. You
can play games on a board. You can play
cutting, which is very popular.
And you can play a radio. Now, the
miracle is suddenly everyone has a
radio.
It's truly a miracle.
And so, I remember, uh
the joke I like to tell is I I was
having a little trouble with one of the
ex
with an abbot who's passed away since
then.
Uh we had some disagreements about
whether all the monks deserved water or
not.
And uh
and I paid for the water system and I
built it.
And uh so, anyway,
uh so,
this is how I became his best friend.
Uh
I went to uh his room to have a
discussion with him.
And it was Guyi.
And he's Here's this very stiff
abbot sitting on the floor sprawled out
with his robes everywhere.
And he's playing a board game with one
of the young monks, you know.
And I'm like, it it
it came out of my mouth,
uh me la chu sho na ka ka de.
Say me la.
Me la.
Sorry, chu la.
Chu la.
Me sho na.
De ka de.
Chula
Mayshana
The Khadijah
What the hell, you know? If water
catches fire, what are we going to do?
How are you going to put it out?
You understand?
If the guy in charge of making sure
kids don't play games in the masjid is
playing a game, you know, the kids
then who Who am I going to call to
report it?
It's him.
That really made me popular with this
guy.
Uh
Why am I bringing that up?
Boy, crap. The older you get, the more
stories you have.
I'll give you a class about emptiness.
I better tell you real soon than finish
the class. Uh
If you're a Buddhist
and if you're studying emptiness
and as you study emptiness
you have the instinct that emptiness is
coming from its own side, you have
destroyed the only antidote in the
world.
A a miseducated Buddhist is more
dangerous than anybody.
A wrongly educated Buddhist is a truly
dangerous thing.
A Buddhist using mantras who doesn't
understand why the mantra works is
dangerous,
Because they go around selling something
that doesn't work. It's like a person
who sells fire extinguishers that don't
work. What could be more cynical
than to sell fire extinguishers that
that you know they don't work,
you know? What could be more
more cruel
than to go sell 100 fire extinguishers,
then the place catches on fire and
and it doesn't work, you know? So,
in a way, we must educate ourselves
about what emptiness really is because
if you
if you come to misunderstand emptiness,
it will never work for you.
And then you'll always suffer. Okay, got
it?
Uh same with mantras. Okay, yay.
If the water catches fire, if the
emptiness
is self- If you think the emptiness is
self-existing, then
then we can't fix anything.
Okay, got it?
All right.
I don't know if you remember this one. I
I I don't remember if I really nailed it
down. I think some of the pictures we
skipped, right, Puji? I'm sorry.
Uh
anyway, um
we are in the chapter We're in a new
chapter, 14, about sansarga. My Sanskrit
expert just went to the bathroom with
me.
What's sansarga?
It means contact. Contact between
things, okay? Like how do things touch
each other? And it It feels correctly
that a lot of Nagarjuna depends on this
question, right? Can anything touch
another thing?
Okay?
And uh
I I
I'll tell you what Nagarjuna would say
about this picture.
If you want money bad enough to hurt
someone to get it, you cannot touch the
If you want money bad enough
to compete with someone else to get the
money,
then you will never touch The money
cannot touch your hand.
Okay, got it? Does that mean you can't
hold money?
No, it just means the money is unreal.
Why?
It looks like you got it by taking it,
but you didn't. You got it by being
generous. You got it by making a
donation to Club Doru last week.
And the money you think you stole
isn't the money
you stole. This is the money you got cuz
you donated last week. Got it?
But she doesn't she doesn't have any
money in her hands.
Cuz she thinks it came from stealing,
but it didn't. It can't.
Okay? All right. Next one.
And bing bing bing bing bing bing.
Uh what was this lesson? Do you guys
remember?
Yeah, but but with what with what
context?
And you have shortness without
Yeah, can you recognize
what?
Can you recognize shortness?
Yeah, without a tall person. And the
Buddhist standard is
Yes.
Yeah, because it's coming from your
mind. Okay? And like
I I've heard the weird explanations by
American untrained Buddhists who say uh
oh, Buddhism is all about uh in fact, I
mean, I wrote a book about it.
Uh
oh, Buddhism is all about uh
comparison. What do you call it?
Short you can't see
short comes from a long. Basically, it
was saying that everything is dependence
dependent origination means you can't
recognize short until you have long. And
that's completely false and
Buddha never said anything like that.
Uh in fact, the Buddha would say the
opposite.
Which is what?
You can think something is long without
something which is short cuz it's coming
from your mind.
That's all.
It doesn't depend on two outside objects
comparing them.
That's not where short comes from. Short
comes from your mind. You can have lots
of shorts without talls.
All of it.
Okay.
All right.
And you can find those books. It's
amazing.
It's amazing. Okay.
Okay, next one.
I don't know if you remember, but
let's go back to the easiest example,
okay?
Uh there's a part of the path that you
walked on
already.
There's a part of the path that you
didn't reach yet.
And there's a part of the path between,
okay? Does the part of the path By the
way, this chapter is about samsara,
which means
contact. Can the part of the path that
you already walked on ever make contact
with the part of the path that you're
going to walk on?
No.
Cannot, okay?
Unless you don't look so close.
And that's a Buddhist principle. Okay?
Unless you don't look so close. Matak
machipa. Say matak.
Matak.
Machipa.
Without investigation.
Without checking.
I mean, if you if you're worried
if you're trying to drive back to
Rimrock this afternoon to get your map
on time
uh
and you sit there and worry about which
part of the road did you already drive
on, which part of the road you didn't
drive on, you're going to get in a car
accident, you're never going to get
home, okay? There are appropriate times
in our life when you should just god
damn drive home
and don't worry about where you were.
Okay, you're going to get in a car
anyway.
So, it's called matak machipa, okay?
Does the
Does the part of the path that Does the
part of the road to Rimrock that I
already drove on ever touch the Do they
ever intersect? That's the point.
Uh
ever touch the part of the road I
haven't driven on yet? Look, there's
times in life when you don't want to
have to worry about it. Just don't hit
the traffic in the Easter holiday.
Don't crash into anybody. When you get
home, before your nap, you can think
about Okay, matak machipa means
Do they
Yes, if you don't look at it too
closely. Okay, if you don't look at it
too closely. Very famous British
principle.
Okay.
Should I do my mantras? Should I do
mantras?
Look, relax and do your mantras. But
they don't work. I know they don't work,
but they're going to work. Just be nice
to people, your mantra is going to work.
Ah, okay, good. I don't have to stop my
mantras. Geshe La never said don't do
mantras. Geshe La said, do mantras with
wisdom.
And then they work. Okay. But what if I
don't have wisdom, can I still do my
mantras? Yes. Will it help me? Yeah,
your intention is very powerful. Okay.
Go ahead, but later try to study
why they work, which is this book. Okay.
All right. Uh by the way, this is the
most famous book about why mantras work.
In fact, the author was
the highest
tantric guy in Indian history. Duh.
Okay.
Maybe there's a connection.
All right. 8,000 pages of books about
his ideas of tantra. Maybe he knew what
he was talking about.
Okay. All right.
What's the next picture? Tell me a
story, somebody.
The rare coin.
Uh okay.
Yeah. Now, tell me the story, come on.
Don't make me repeat the story.
Geshe La used to drive
Yeah, Geshe La used to drive his llama.
He drove to Washington
for 20 years. Every month.
500 times.
And you always stopped.
Yeah, we stopped at Howard Johnson next
to Delaware Bridge. Probably they're
going to have to put a plaque there now.
Uh
and Rinpoche would say, "Tell the lady I
don't want the
artificial
cream."
Okay. Uh meaning if it's created
it's not natural. We are creating the
world.
Uh,
it's very similar to powdered cream as
opposed to real cream. Okay?
Does it work? Well, that's a question.
Okay. Next picture. Uh,
by the way, we moved on to chapter 15,
which called an an investigation of rang
shin.
For a hundred bucks, Tim, give me a nice
translation for rang shin in this case.
Which means it's not the one you
normally knew.
It's not a It's not
I'll almost say it for you. It's not
nature here. I mean, there's a better
word you could use.
Well, what's so mixed up with this in
nature?
Give me the word.
We found a better word in fact I'm going
to change my translation. Uh,
Anyway, identity.
Okay. Do things have an identity? Okay.
Do they have a natural identity? Okay.
And the first example we have is
somebody explain the example to me.
Is this the last picture by the way? No,
we still have some more.
Okay.
What's happening here?
Two ways to fall off.
In the kitchen, when you're having an
argument with your husband, there's two
extremes you can fall off. First one,
which is the one that everyone falls
off.
What's the most common misunderstanding
when you're having an argument with your
husband?
It's not coming from me. I don't know
what's wrong with him today. He's
hungry, he had a bad day, there was a
lot of traffic. You make up all these
reasons why he's being mean to you.
Okay? Then,
that's one extreme. All right?
He's coming from his own side.
Now, the second extreme is only
fallen into by un- by badly trained
Buddhist.
It doesn't exist.
Yeah, if he's if he's not coming from
his side, you always have to say if.
If he's not coming from his side, then
he don't exist in Maya, illusion. He's
not there at all, you know, okay, all
right.
If the mantra doesn't exist the way I
thought it existed, there the mantra
there is no mantra.
If the mantra doesn't work the way I
thought it did, there is no mantra,
okay? That you fell off of both
edges of the bridge. What's the proper
attitude about the mantra?
It does work, but only
if I
try to protect love. If I try to protect
Yeah, if I load it like a stapler. Okay,
good. All right, nice answers.
Let's go. We're almost done. Hang in
there.
The next chapter 16, by the way, we only
get to 17, we're done, okay? Yay.
was called an investigation of bondage
and freedom from bondage, okay? Chained
up and breaking the chains, okay? Like
Schwarzenegger.
Okay.
And this picture was called
removing the hand- handcuffs from a
nobody, and it means
who
Who's chained to what?
Okay. Yeah.
Yeah, I'm chained to
Or Yeah, good. Or my body and mind.
I'm chained to a mortal body.
As you get older, it becomes serious,
you know. When you're younger, it's
like, okay.
But when you're later, you're like
the body's falling apart, and then you
realize you're chained to it. You cannot
get away from it.
And your mind is also you're chained to
your to your mind.
And neither one is healthy
and they are falling apart. And then you
can't get away. You're chained to it.
Okay. All right. So, then the guardian
will say, "No.
The thing you think you're chained to
is not real.
You are chained to something you
produced. You are chained to something
you are seeing get old
because you didn't take care of your
seeds. So, just take care of your seeds
and you won't be chained anymore.
Got it?
Okay.
That's freedom from bondage.
Next one, you guys.
This is chapter 17. Yay, we reached the
last chapter. The chapter of the
investigation of
karma, okay, which is a long chapter.
And we're going We spent a couple of
classes on it. Two or three classes.
Uh so,
this represents chetana and chetayitva.
Yeah. Karma in the form of
Yeah. Karma in the form of intention.
And then what you did, either good or
bad intention, okay? So,
when Buddha taught karma, it's
interesting, I think,
that the guardian of first talks about
karma in the context of thinking and
doing what you thought to do.
He He doesn't say 10 kinds of deeds or
something like that. He says, "All the
All karma is divided into
what you're thinking
and what you thought to do, okay?
Which is very What's cool?
Lalitavistara, okay? Didn't he say
Mahayana teaching?
Abhidharma. Why is he so fixated on
Abhidharma?
The other schools didn't exist yet.
Okay.
No mind on this guy yet. No, stop trying
to get schooled yet.
He's early. This stuff is old.
Okay, this stuff is 2,000 years old. The
fact that you can read it 100
generations later, that's like
something. That says something about the
lineage.
The lineage has been kept. It's a very
beautiful. Okay.
You Normally, you can't even talk to
your parents, right?
Now, I mean, multiply that times 100.
It's a miracle that we can read this
thing. Okay.
It's It's really says something about
the lineage.
The The
The It says something about the
the function of the lineage. You You
kept it for 2,000 years. It's It's
unbelievable. Okay.
All right. Uh yeah, two kinds of karma.
Thinking
and what the thinking inspires you to
do.
Next one.
$100. Somebody tell me why this is
relevant.
$100. God, I'm giving away so much
money. You guys aren't excited. You're
still like
When you walked into the bathroom,
are you the same person
when you walked in?
And do I sound it?
I said there's seven types
Say again.
I said there's seven types of karma.
That's a good guess, but it's wrong.
What scene was happening in this chapter
that might be shown in this picture?
What is this picture? What's happening?
It's a waiting room.
Yeah.
Basically, you're going to come back.
Yeah, good. Okay. Yay! $100 for the
young man. You're getting a lot of money
today.
Yeah. Where Where does the karma stay
until it ripens? Okay. What's the Okay,
to earn $100 now,
if it
was if the karma was
There's two problems. If it was this
If it was unchanging
Yeah, how can it can
Yeah, how Yeah, it couldn't produce
anything. And if it was changing if
If it was No, if it was going in and out
of existence
then how can it sustain how can it
ripen? Okay, got it?
All right.
How does karma wait
until it opens?
Okay, good.
That's a big issue.
Okay, and this helps to answer that
question for $100.
The next picture helps to answer the
question.
Chut me tsawa. $100, what's it mean?
Yeah, but what's that mean?
Hey, work it out then you can share the
money.
You have to have a chut me tsawa.
You have to have this contract. What's
the contract say?
Don't go away or something.
Yeah, A A
don't go away. Okay, A doesn't go away.
Okay, what doesn't go away?
The karma, it stays with you until it
ripens until it opens. There's a
contractual agreement between you and
your karma.
As soon as you
do how many things?
Anything.
Okay, as soon as you do anything you get
a corresponding don't go away.
I forget what we call it.
As soon as you do As soon as you pick
your nose, you just made like 10 don't
go aways.
And they stay with you, okay? And they
help explain why
the karma, you know, whether it changes
or it doesn't change, it stays with you
because there's glue. It's a glue. It's
a contractual agreement between you and
your karmic seeds. You stick with me
until you open, okay? Yeah, okay.
Let's write a contract. Okay.
Okay, you write a contract with your
karmas.
And they stick with you until they open.
Okay, right.
Next picture.
Something rotten is making something
run.
It had to do with the first Arya truth.
And the second Arya truth. Second Arya
truth has two parts.
First Arya truth is truth of suffering.
The money's going down, down, down,
down.
Huh?
There's two part What karma?
Arya truth of suffering. Karma
Yeah. Yeah, karma and negative emotions,
okay? Karma and negative emotions.
If the
If the cause is crappy, then the
result is crappy, okay? If the apple is
rotten, then the apple pie that you made
from it is going to taste bad, right?
Okay? What's that mean? If the karma and
the negative emotions are
impure,
meaning
good, self-existent, how could they make
a
Yeah, how could they make a pure result?
How could you get
How could you get a changing result from
a unchanging
action.
Okay?
If If their action was not empty,
then the action would be If the action
had an identity,
then it couldn't change. And but it And
if it still made a result, life would be
weird. Then you'd have to be really
super careful because
results would pop up without doing
anything. And even in the normal world,
they would complain if you get
Watermelon.
Watermelon No, lettuce growing all over
the
yard, which you didn't plant. Even in
the normal world, people say something's
weird.
Got it?
Okay.
All right. I think we have one more
picture movie.
No. Is that the last picture?
Oh, okay. Did we do the last picture?
Oh, we didn't do the movie picture.
Let's do it. I'll explain it, and we'll
We'll call it a day.
Okay?
This is uh
Okay.
Yeah, you can make some money here.
$300. Last thing. Last part of the
course. Then I'm free.
Then Grandpa can go home and take a nap.
Or have a 20-minute sleep. Uh
For $300,
I'll tell you what the picture was
about, okay?
The picture was about
Do you realize this picture was What do
you call it? Sc- um
scripted.
It's not The picture's not real.
Somebody paid somebody to come and stand
there so they could take a picture of
them making a movie.
Okay?
So, you got a
It's all fake.
The This picture is fake.
Somebody paid somebody to pretend they
were making a movie.
And the movie is
also pretending.
Got it? Isn't it a clever picture? Come
on, give me some credit.
Okay, now listen. This is not a picture
of people making a movie. It's all fake.
Somebody paid them to come and stand
there. They took a picture. They charged
me $5 for this picture.
Cuz it's fake, okay? It's a fake picture
of somebody making a
fake picture. For $300, tell me the
connection to the last part of the stuff
that we study.
Your life.
When did you pay me?
What's the LAST THING WE TALKED about in
the last class?
The last thing is fake to begin with.
Yeah, but what was the example? Come on.
That God made an apple in the
Yeah, it's a different apple.
Boy, that's a short attention period.
What apple were we talking about in the
last class? At the end of the last
class.
Say again.
No.
What apple were we talking about?
In school.
We talked about an apple tree.
I don't know. The elimination?
Yeah, keep going. You're going to make
300 bucks. Keep going. Keep going.
Yeah.
There was a tree
There also was a tree
emanated by
emanated by the Buddha.
Is it the Buddha?
No.
It's not a really Buddha cuz you can't
climb Buddha and pick his tree.
Then what happened with the What did the
tree do?
It um
Made a
apple.
apple. And what did the apple do?
Made a worm.
Okay. How many
How many real trees, apples, and worms
there.
Zero.
Why is that relevant to the discussion
of karma?
You already got $300, but somebody can
help you.
Why are we talking about that?
The other guy said, "Look, if it's fake,
it's not karma and and and result."
And we said,
"All karma results are fake. Come on.
You told me Buddha can emanate?
That That's also fake, but it's real,
isn't it? You can climb the tree. You
can eat the apple. Okay? That's why the
worm is there.
What do the tree, the apple, and the
worm represent
in karma? In karma.
What's the three things going on in
karma? Similar to the path you haven't
walked on, similar to the path you
walked on, similar to the impossible
line between them.
Same thing.
Somebody does something.
It
creates
continues, and then it
opens. Got it? Cool.
It's all It's all unreal,
but it's
you can use it.
It's all unreal, but you can use it.
That's all. Okay? Thanks. When you do
the Medicine Buddha mantra, and you
cause and you cure someone's cancer,
it's totally possible, but only if it's
empty.
Okay? Only if the energy of the mantra
is coming from treating
from saving life,
from respecting all life on this planet.
Then you get power to the
mantra, and then the mantra can cure
somebody's cancer. But if you don't
understand that,
then the mantra's kind of like
you know, paper house or something. It's
you know, it's there, but it's it's not
good luck if you want to keep the rain
out or something.
Okay? Got it? Okay.
Understand that a mantra is an empty,
and you have to put your karma into it
and then it will work. Okay? So So you
can't just sit around and do mantras
without
trying to save the environment. I mean,
that's a simple way to help 80 billion
living creatures. Okay? Right? Plant a
tree,
then do your mantras. Yay! That would be
a real tree.
Okay. So thanks for coming to the
garden. Of course, I'd like to thank Tim
for I don't know. My God.
He's really a master
to get things done and I don't know how
he does all the things he does. It's
kind of must be ammunition.
And then Apatheia and Pal, thank you for
coming from Mexico and helping us to
film and it makes it fun also.
It's a lot more fun for me if I have
more friends here. Thank you, Rebecca,
for coming to from Los Angeles to help
run the whole thing with your great
cinematics and photog graphic skills.
Thank you, remember I have to for
driving me here and paying all my bills,
especially my student debt bills.
And thank you, Gelson, for Diamond
Mountain and for keeping this building
in a good shape so we can have these
classes here. Yay! Thanks to everybody.
And Christina Casica
for keeping all our stomachs filled
during the filming. So we had a great
team here
and I really am I am really grateful.
And thank you for Thank you, Tony Lama,
and thank you, John Brady, for
saving Tony Lama. Okay? All right. See
you guys later.
Yay!